Okay, today's דף Daf is פ, Pe, בבא קמא Bava Kamma 80,
and we pick up at the bottom of ע"ט עמוד ב' Ayin
Tet Amud Bet and an interesting משנה Mishna to wrap up מרובה,
Meruba, maybe wrapping up a lot of the stuff before about all
types of damages and stealing. And here are some general תקנות Takkanot
or rules that the Rabbis put in place for society in order
to protect people's property. Let's take a look.
אין מגדלין בהמה דקה בארץ ישראל אבל מגדלין בסוריא ובמדברות שבארץ ישראל.
Ein megadlin behema dakka be-Eretz Yisrael aval megadlin be-Suriya u-ve-midbarot she-be-Eretz Yisrael.
You do not raise בהמה דקה, behema dakka, which refers to sheep
and goat, in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Why? Because sheep and goat
are grazing animals and they can, you know, destroy the vegetation. They
can, and particularly in a place like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael where
it does not have a lot of grass and vegetation, they can
be very destructive. And therefore it was completely forbidden to raise them
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but you can raise them in סוריא,
Suriya, like Syria, areas that at various times were, you know, had
Jewish settlements in the time of the משנה, Mishna, and in the
forests of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael because there apparently the damage that
they would do would be relatively minor. Okay. ואין
מגדלין תרנגולין בירושלים מפני הקדשים. Ve-ein megadlin tarnegolin be-Yerushalayim mipnei ha-kodashim. You
cannot raise chickens in Jerusalem because chickens, you know, are pecking all
over the place and they will be bringing different types of bugs
from like the garbage dumps. And because there are meat of sacrifices
and קדשים kodashim all over Jerusalem, this they will become טמא. tamei.
So it's too much of a hazard. ולא כהנים בארץ ישראל מפני
הטהרות. Velo kohanim be-Eretz Yisrael mipnei ha-teharot. And כהנים kohanim cannot raise
chickens anywhere in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael because they have תרומה terumah
outside of Jerusalem. They have things that have to keep טהור tahor
and the chickens will make sure, will be bringing things from the
garbage dump or whatever which will make it טמא. tamei. אין מגדלין
חזירים בכל מקום. Ein megadlin chazirin be-chol makom. You should not raise
pigs in any place. And we will see the reason in the
גמרא. Gemara. It's not just that they're non-kosher animals, then it would
have sort of said any non-kosher animal. So whether in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael or out of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you can't raise
pigs. לא יגדל אדם את הכלב אלא אם כן היה קשור בשלשלת.
Lo yegadel adam et ha-kelev ela im ken haya kashur be-shalshelet. And
don't raise a dog unless it was, you know, chained down. We
had a משנה Mishna somewhat similar to this earlier on and that's
sort of a concern obviously that the dog will go out and
bite somebody and injure somebody. רש"י Rashi also says that it will
bark and it will scare somebody out of fright and could lead
to a miscarriage. אין פורסין נשובין ליונים אלא אם כן היה רחוק
מן הישוב ל' ריס. Ein parsin nishovin le-yonim ela im ken haya
rachok min ha-yishuv shloshim ris. You do not lay out traps for
pigeons unless it was thirty ריס ris out of the town, out
of where people were dwelling. Thirty ריס ris is רש"י Rashi says
four מיל, mil, which is about four kilometers. And because you do
not want to inadvertently be catching somebody else's pigeons. You can catch
wild ones, but not somebody else's pigeons. Okay, interesting collection of things
to sort of wrap up the first seven פרקים. prakim. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן אין מגדלין בהמה דקה
בארץ ישראל אבל מגדלין בחורשין שבארץ ישראל. Tanu Rabbanan ein megadlin behema
dakka be-Eretz Yisrael aval megadlin be-chorshin she-be-Eretz Yisrael. You do not raise
small animals, again specifically refers to sheep and goat, in ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, but you can raise them in the, you know, in
the forests בחורשין שבארץ ישראל. be-chorshin she-be-Eretz Yisrael. בסוריא אפילו בישוב. Be-Suriya
afilu be-yishuv.
And in סוריא Suriya you can do it even in the settled
area. I want to apologize, I think in the משנה Mishna I
said מדברות. midbarot. מדברות, Midbarot,
I jumped ahead and I was referring to the גמרא Gemara that
said forests. מדברות Midbarot does not refer to deserts in the משנה.
Mishna. מדברות Midbarot refers to animals, like you know, when you're driving
out in the Judean hills, that's considered מדברות, midbarot, places that there's
not much vegetation. But at certain times of the year, you know
when you're driving out in the Judean hills, you'll often see shepherds,
you know,
Bedouins and whatever shepherds you know with their sheep and goat and
there vegetation crops up at certain times of the year and that's
a place for
grazing and we're not concerned that there it will cause damage. So
מדברות midbarot are okay and the forests, that's in the משנה, Mishna,
and the forests are okay.
Alright. בסוריא אפילו בישוב. Be-Suriya afilu be-yishuv. You can even do it
even in where people are settled because we're not concerned about the,
you know, land in סוריא. Suriya. I mean if you damage the
land, you know that's your own property, or obviously you have to
be careful, and תוספות Tosefot discusses a general concern about grazing and
grazing in other people's lands, that's not the concern here. So obviously
you have to be careful never to go on other people's lands
and if you want to damage your own property, that's your business
and presumably public lands were not seen as a concern or not
enough of a concern to make a גזירה gezeira and a תקנה
takkanah to prevent people from doing it, except in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael where they obviously had a high motivation to try to protect
the quality of the land. And okay, ואין צריך לומר בחוצה לארץ
Ve'ein tzarich lomar b'chutza aretz and if we are not going to
be concerned about סוריא Surya which borders on Israel and to some
times, some degree might have some קדושה kedusha which is a different
discussion, then certainly in real חוץ לארץ chutz l'aretz there will be
no problem raising sheep and goats. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we turned
another ברייתא: baraita: אין מגדלין בהמה דקה בארץ ישראל אבל מגדלין במדברות
שביהודה ובמדברות שבספר עכו. Ein megadlin behema daka b'Eretz Yisrael aval megadlin
b'midbarot she'bi'Yehuda u'v'midbarot she'b'Sfar Akko. Okay, and this is going back to
the משנה Mishna which is the מדברות. midbarot. Okay, you do not
raise small animals in Israel, but you can raise them in the
Judean hills, you know, the Judean more dry land, and similar in
the מדבר midbar that is by the border of עכו. Akko. ואף
על פי שאמרו אין מגדלין בהמה דקה, אבל מגדלין בהמה גסה, V'af
al pi she'amru ein megadlin behema daka, aval megadlin behema gassa, and
even though they said this about small animals, אבל מגדלין בהמה גסה,
aval megadlin behema gassa, you can raise large animals like cows and
this would also presumably, it sounds from רש"י, Rashi, include donkeys and
horses, anything that's not sheep and goats. Why? לפי שאין גוזרין גזרה
על הציבור אלא אם כן רוב הציבור יכולים לעמוד בה, Lefi she'ein
gozrin gezeirah al hatzibur ela im ken rov hatzibur yecholim la'amod bah,
because that would be something that would not be tolerable by the
broader community. You don't make an edict that the community cannot stand
by. Why can the community not stand by it? בהמה דקה אפשר
להביא מחוצה לארץ. Behema daka efshar l'havi mi'chutz l'aretz. If small animals
you can bring, meaning why would you want a sheep? You would
want it for the wool or maybe the milk, you know,
which you make cheese out of, and to eat. Okay, so all
of that stuff you can import and you don't have to raise
it yourself.
אבל בהמה גסה אי אפשר להביא מחוצה לארץ, Aval behema gassa ee
efshar l'havi mi'chutz l'aretz, but a large animal you can't bring from
חוץ לארץ. chutz l'aretz. Now why not? Because we're not just talking
about meat and milk, you know, we're talking about cows for plowing
and horses for riding and donkeys for, you know, for beasts of
burden and mules and so on. So those things you cannot prohibit,
but the sheep and goat at least you can try to prohibit.
How successful this was is not clear. Okay, ואף על פי שאמרו
אין מגדלין בהמה דקה, אבל משוהין אותם לפני הרגל שלושים יום. V'af
al pi she'amru ein megadlin behema daka, aval mash'hin otam lifnei ha'regel
shloshim yom. Even though you're not allowed to raise them, you know,
you're allowed to purchase them and before יום טוב, Yom Tov, because
יום טוב, Yom Tov, you know, that's when you would have meat.
You wouldn't normally have it during the year, maybe you'd have chicken,
you know, and people, how often do people slaughter a cow? But,
you know, so a small animal like a sheep or a goat,
that you might have for יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you can
buy it and therefore, and you're allowed to buy it within thirty
days before. That's not considered raising, even though you're going to have
to feed it for those thirty days, it's only a maximum of
thirty days and therefore we will allow you. We don't force you
to buy it the day before יום טוב. Yom Tov. משוהין אותם
לפני הרגל שלושים יום וקודם משתה בנו שלושים יום, Mash'hin otam lifnei
ha'regel shloshim yom v'kodem mishteh b'no shloshim yom, and again, if there's
other reasons, you know, your son is getting married, so you are
allowed to buy these animals, you're not only buy the meat, you're
allowed to buy the live animals and you have thirty days before
the event. Okay, but not longer, that would be considered getting into
the category of raising the animals. ובלבד שלא ישהה אחרונה שבהם שלושים
יום. U'vilvad she'lo yisheh achrona shebahem shloshim yom. Now you cannot let
the last one, meaning if you bought a couple of animals and
for יום טוב, Yom Tov, then and you didn't maybe buy them
all at the same time, you can't sort of say, "Well, the
last one I bought ten days before יום טוב, Yom Tov, I
get twenty days till after יום טוב." Yom Tov. No. Okay, and
now the גמרא Gemara explains what that means. And here clearly you'll
see the shift to Aramaic, this is the גמרא's Gemara's gloss on
this: דסלקא דעתך אמינא, D'salka daitach amina, I would have thought to
say: דנפק ליה רגל ומיזבנא עד השתא אכתי לא מלו לה תלתין
יומין, D'nafak lei regel u'mizvna ad hashta achati lo malu leh tlatin
yomin, that even if the רגל regel is over, but maybe even
if after the רגל regel is over, if from the time you
bought it until now it's not thirty days, לא נימא תלתין מששרי
ליה לשהייה, lo nema tlatin mish'sharei lei l'shahayei, don't think that you
have thirty days to, you know, if you bought it before the
רגל, regel, you have thirty days from the time you purchased it
regardless. No, that's not true. אלא כיון דנפק ליה רגל לא מיבעי
ליה לשהייה, Ela kivan d'nafak leh regel lo miba'ei lei l'shahayei, once
the רגל regel is over you don't have a right to do
it. So you can buy it up to thirty days before the
רגל, regel, but once the רגל regel is over you are no
longer allowed to be holding on to it. Okay, top of פ"א,
peh alef, והטבח לוקח ושוחט לוקח ושוהה, Ve'hatabbach lokeiach v'shochet lokeiach v'shoh-eh,
and a butcher can go ahead and purchase it and שחט, shacht,
obviously turn it right into meat, and he's also allowed to, you
know, purchase it and not שחט shacht it right away, ובלבד שלא
ישהה את האגונה שבהם ל' יום, u'vilvad she'lo yisheh et ha'aguna shebahem
lamed yom, as long as you don't allow the אגונה, aguna, which
is an interesting word, the last one thirty days. It's an interesting
question what this means. רש"י Rashi says thirty days before the שוק,
shuk, תוספות Tosafot just says it just means, you know, thirty days
before, you know, it's not referring specifically to a שוק, shuk, nobody
mentioned like a special market day, and it just means that
you have to sell them or שחט shacht them within thirty days.
And אגונה aguna here means, at least according to תוספות, Tosafot, it
means the one that's left alone after you sell all the rest.
All right. And so that's like an אגונה, aguna, although אגונה aguna
usually comes from the word עוגן ogen which means like an anchor
or a woman who's chained. Here we're understanding it to mean the
last one. Okay, second line from the top פ"א. peh alef. שאלו
תלמידיו את רבן גמליאל, Sha'alu talmidav et Rabban Gamliel, Rabban Gamliel's students
asked him: מהו לעשות. mahu la'asot. מה לגדל, Mah l'gadel, מה לגדל,
Mah l'gadel,
are you allowed to like raise, you know, small animals? אמר להן,
Amar lahen, מותר. Mutar. You're allowed. והתנן אין מגדלין, V'ha-tnan ein megadlin,
but it says you're not allowed to raise sheep and goat. אלא
הכי קבעי מיניה. Ela hachi ka-ba'ei minei. No, no. So this must
be what they what they asked him. מה לשהות, Mah l'shahot, are
you allowed to not raise them but purchase them and keep them
around for, you know, a certain period of time until you're ready
to use them? אמר להן, Amar lahen, מותר. Mutar. It's permitted, ובלבד
שלא תצא ותרעה בעדר, u'bilvad shelo tetze v'tireh ba'eder, as long as
you don't go ahead and bring it out and have it graze,
meaning so you can, you know, you can feed it at home,
but even when you're allowed to have it there for 30 days,
if presumably we're talking in the same context as before, תוספות Tosafot
assume it's the same context as before like before the רגל, regel,
he's not arguing and he's just clarifying that when you're allowed to
buy it before using it, you can't go ahead and graze it,
you can bring it food but you can't bring it out to
graze. אלא קושרה בכרעי המטה. Ela kosherah b'kar'ei hamitah. You tie it
to the to the legs of the bed.
תוספות Tosafot says again that this is not meaning literally it has
to be that way, but that was a common thing they did.
The basic point is don't take it out to graze. So תוספות
Tosafot says he's qualifying, he's limiting the permission of buying like it
before your, you know, before יום טוב Yom Tov 30 days. רש"י
Rashi says that he's actually being more lenient and he would allow
even without a special circumstance because no special circumstance is mentioned here,
he would allow you to buy it as long as you make
sure not to not to graze it. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
מעשה בחסיד אחד שהיה גונח מלבו ושאלו לרופאים. Ma'aseh b'chasid echad shehayah
gone'ach milibo v'sha'alu l'rofim. A certain righteous person, you know, had this
was groaning from his heart and they asked the doctors what to
do. ואמרו אין לו תקנה עד שינק חלב רותח משחרית לשחרית. V'amru
ein lo takanah ad sheyanok chalav rote'ach mishachrit l'shachrit.
He has to suckle boiling milk from morning to morning, meaning whether
it means directly suckle it from, you know, the animal itself or
as soon as you express the milk from the animal drink it
right away while it's still boiling, but that's what he has to
do. You know it has the body temperature of the animal while
it's still hot right after it came out of the animal. והביאו
לו עז, V'hevi'u lo ez,
so they brought him a goat, וקשרו לו בכרעי המטה, v'kashru lo
b'kar'ei hamitah, and they tied it to the leg of the bed.
Just like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said before. So certainly according to
רש"י, Rashi, this is in line with רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, you
know, and he had certainly a need for this, it shouldn't be
worse than the whole שלושים יום shloshim yom before the רגל, regel,
although this will be ongoing, but nevertheless he's, you know, there's a
legitimate need and he's not taking it out to have it graze.
Okay. והיה יונק ממנה משחרית לשחרית, V'hayah yonek mimenah mishachrit l'shachrit, and
he would suckle from it from morning to morning. Sounds like directly
from the animal. Okay. לימים נכנסו חביריו לבקרו. L'yamim nichnesu chaveirav l'vakro.
And then some of his friends came to visit him, maybe they
heard he was sick. כיון שראו אותו העז קשורה בכרעי המטה, Keivan
she-ra'u oto ha'ez kshurah b'kar'ei hamitah, they saw this goat tied up
to the leg of the bed. חזרו לאחוריהם Chazru l'achoreihem and they
recoiled backwards, ואמרו ליסטים מזוין בביתו של זה, v'amru listim mezuyan b'veito
shel zeh,
there's an armed bandit in this house and maybe the ליסטים מזוין
listim mezuyan has to do with also what it's doing in מרובה,
Merubah, these animals are considered like robbers and you know they're armed
robbers, you know they're armed with their teeth I guess. Okay, this
person has an armed robber in his house? ואנו נכנסים אצלו, V'anu
nichnasim etzlo, we should go sit with him? You know we should
go into this house? This thing is like a danger to the
whole, you know, landscape of ישראל Yisrael and we have to totally,
you know, be off it. And again, maybe that's why it's חסיד
אחד, chasid echad, maybe a normal person it would be okay, you
know one really wonders how different is it than the case before
about buying it before the רגל. regel. Okay, he's not bringing it
outside and so on, but maybe for a חסיד chasid and maybe
for his friends this was like had to be totally taboo, totally
off-limits. ישבו ובדקו ולא מצאו בו אלא אותו עון של אותה עז.
Yashvu u'vadku v'lo matzu bo ela oto avon shel otah ez.
They went and they examined, I don't know why they're examining, but
they thought like oh maybe we were wrong to be friends with
him, we thought he was so righteous, but nope, they found that
this was the only thing that he had ever done wrong. ואף
הוא בשעת מיתתו אמר, V'af hu b'sha'at mitato amar,
and even when he was dying he said, יודע אני שאין בי
עון אלא עון אותה עז שעברתי על דברי חברי. Yodei'a ani she'ein
bi avon ela avon otah ez she'avarti al divrei chaveirai. I know
I have no other sin except this goat which I went against
the words of my friends. Now going against the words of my
friends does not sound like it's objectively, you know, totally אסור. assur.
So it seems here the גמרא Gemara does not really explicate this,
but it seems here we're dealing with some, you know, gray area
where obviously, you know, my God, and if the guy was like
פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh or something, but even if he was just
sick, you know you could certainly understand that, but maybe it's saying
it's not מידת חסידות. midat chasidut. Okay. אמר רבי ישמעאל. Amar Rabbi
Yishmael. Said רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, מבעלי בתים שבגליל
העליון היו בית אבא,
Miba'alei batim
shebagalil ha'elyon hayu beit aba, or some say ברבי שמעון שזורי, b'Rabbi
Shimon Shazuri, my father's house was from the, you know, one of
the homeowners, the wealthy people in the Upper Galilee. ומה נחרבו, U'mah
necheravu, and why did their, you know, was there, they lose their
wealth and was their homes destroyed? שהיו מורין בחורשין, Shehayu morin bachorshin,
that they would go ahead and they would, you know, have their
animals graze in the, in the desert, in the, excuse me, I
keep on flipping it, graze in the forests. Okay, we're going to
see what the problem is, the משנה Mishnah says you're allowed to.
שהיו מורין בחרשין she'hayu morin be'charashin that they would go ahead and
they would you know have their animals graze in the in the
desert in the excuse me I keep on flipping it graze in
the forests okay we're going to see what the problem is the
משנה Mishnah says you're allowed to graze in the forest ודנים דיני
ממונות ביחיד ve'danim dinei mamonot be'yachid and they would you know judge
דיני ממונות dinei mamonot as an individual and you know they're halachically
technically allowed to be a דיין יחיד dayan yachid to be דן
דיני ממונות dan dinei mamonot but it's not appropriate, things that get
discussed in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, ואף על פי שהיו להם חורשים סמוך לבתיהם
ve'af al pi she'hayu lahem chorshim samuch levateihem and even though they
had, you know, forests near their homes, so what's the problem? They
were only going into the forests, that's allowed. שדה קטנה היתה מעבירן
דרך עליה. Sadeh ktana hayta ma'aviran derech aleha. There's a tiny little
field and they would cross over it, and would the problem be
either that the goats or the sheep would graze in that field
or they would cross through it without permission? Okay, and that's why
my whole father's house would, you know, that they lost all their
wealth, their home was destroyed again and because even though because they
were not super punctilious about these things. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
רועה
שעשה תשובה, Ro'eh she'asah teshuvah, אין מחייבין אותו למכור מיד, ein mechayvin
oto limkor miyad, אלא מוכר על יד על יד. ela mocher al
yad al yad. If a shepherd does תשובה teshuvah and now we're
going to the other point, and תוספות Tosafot raises this and the
גמרא Gemara here is not really touching on it, but a more
general problem of shepherds, you know, concerned that they will bring their
sheep and goats and graze in lands that are not theirs, and
it's a problem of גזל. gezel. That's really not what's being discussed
here at all, it's the concern about the landscape, but okay, but
here we're talking about that yes, he grazes his sheep in other
people's lands, and now he decides he wants to do תשובה. teshuvah.
I don't know how you exactly compute the value of everything that,
you know, he did, but somehow you figure out what that is
and he has to pay back the people that he grazed in
their lands. So you don't obligate him to pay everything back at
once, you know, even if he has the money, you don't go
ahead and, like, you know, you bankrupt him in order to pay
back everybody, אלא מוכר על יד על יד. ela mocher al yad
al yad. You allow him to sell a little bit at a
time, you know, also maybe he would have to sell all of
his sheep, but people see that he's desperate for funds and then
they take advantage of him. So it's sort of like, you know,
bankruptcy, you know, you where you figure out how to do it
in a way that
the creditors get paid back, and he does not go poor and
maybe also is able to get better price for his stuff so
everybody gets paid back and doesn't ruin him. Okay, וכן, ve'chen, and
similarly, גר שנפלו לו כלבים וחזירים בירושתו. ger shenaflo lo klavim ve'chazirim
biyerushato.
If a גר, ger, you know, he inherited from his non-Jewish father
dogs or or pigs, and we're not allowed to raise dogs or
pigs like we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, so he's going to
have to sell it. אין מחייבין אותו למכור מיד. ein mechayvin oto
limkor miyad. You don't force him to get rid of them immediately,
then he'll have to, you know, we won't be able to make
as much money from it, אלא מוכר על יד על יד. ela
mocher al yad al yad. So this is a little different. Here,
you know, on the one hand, he didn't do anything wrong; on
the other hand, like, you know, it's not like our people going
to get paid back or not, is he going to go get
poor or not? Nevertheless, you know, you allow him time so that
he can do it at a way that he can get full
price for it and, you know, and is able to arrange his
his finances accordingly. Okay, וכן מי שנדר ליקח בית וליקח אשה בארץ
ישראל. ve'chen mi shenadar likach bayit velikach isha be'Eretz Yisrael. Somebody made
a נדר neder in order to to purchase a house or to
get married a woman in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Funny that that's
an example, somebody would make that type of a נדר. neder. Okay,
אין מחייבין אותו ליקח מיד, ein mechayvin oto likach miyad, sort of
like making a נדר neder to make עליה. aliyah. אין מחייבין אותו
ליקח מיד. ein mechayvin oto likach miyad. You don't obligate them to
purchase the house immediately or to marry a woman, the first woman
that they
find, עד שימצא ההוגנת לו, ad sheyimtza ha'hogenet lo, until you find
the, you know, the house that's the right house for you to
live in and the woman that's the right woman for you to
marry, obviously speaking to the man. Okay, now but now we're going
to get a story about a woman. So again, all these things
are you give people time in order to do it in the
best possible way, and the last case about a נדר neder is
particularly interesting because maybe the language of the נדר neder might have
suggested, you know, more immediacy, and actually we're going to see a
case where it actually sounds like that sounds like that. Let's take
a look. ומעשה באשה אחת, u'ma'aseh be'isha achat, there was a story
about a particular woman, שהיה בנה מיצר לה, she'haya bna meitzar lah,
that she had a young child, she was like a, it seems
like a widowed woman and she or divorced, and she had a
young child and the, you know, and she needed to be married,
she couldn't handle the child, so she desperately wanted to be married.
וקפצה ונשבעה, vekaptza venishbe'ah, and she jumped up and she took a
שבועה, shevuah, כל מי שיבא איני מחזירתו. kol mi sheyavo eini machziroso.
Whoever comes and proposes to me, I will not refuse him. וקפצו
עליה בני אדם שאינם מהוגנים, vekaptzu aleha bnei adam she'einam mehuganim, so
there's a קפצה kaptza and קפצו. kaptzu. So men that were not
fit jumped up and proposed to her, and you know, people that
were not good matches. כשבא דבר אצל חכמים, kesheba davar etzel chachamim,
so you might think she said I anybody who does it I
won't refuse him, you know, that's more than just the previous case
of a נדר neder to marry a woman or to buy a
house in Israel where there was no time frame or whatever, you
didn't say which house, which woman. Here, she says I won't refuse
anyone. And nevertheless, כשבא דבר אצל חכמים, kesheba davar etzel chachamim, it
came to the sages, אמרו לא נתכוונה זו אלא להגון לה. amru
lo nitkavna zo ela lehagon lah. She only was referring to if
I get an appropriate proposal I will say yes, not an inappropriate
one. Okay, so even if in that case where she said I
won't say no and we mean she means no to a reasonable
offer, then certainly in the case of the house and the woman.
woman when he just does it in Israel you can wait till
you find a proper one. Okay. כשם שאמרו אין מגדלין בהמה דקה,
Keshem she-amru ein megadlin behema daka, the same way you cannot raise
a small, you know, בהמה, behema, you cannot raise a small חיה
דקה khaya daka like a more untamed animal, רש״י Rashi says that
this refers to צביים ושועלים, tzviyim u-shualim, foxes and like deer, okay,
I guess, I don't know, I suppose that they also are grazing
animals. I mean deer, yes, I didn't know about
foxes. Anyway, רבי ישמעאל אומר
מגדלין, Rabbi Yishmael omer megadlin, some say רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar says, מגדלין כלבים כופרין megadlin klavim kufrin you can
raise village dogs, וחתולים ve-khatulim and cats, וקופין ve-kofin and monkeys, וחולדות
סנאים ve-khuldot sna'im and a חולדות סנאים, khuldot sna'im,
certain type of like weasel or something, weasel of the, of the
סנה, sne, of the, you know, of a thorn bush. In the
Koren version of the גמרא Gemara they say here, let me say,
they have a, they call it a חולדות סנאים, khuldot sna'im, they
call it genets or genet. From the description of the גמרא Gemara
this animal be identified as the common genet. This creature which is
biologically similar to the mongoose is the size of a small cat
and has a long tail and very short legs. This animal usually
lived in forested mountains as its flexible body allowed it to climb
easily on trees and rocks. The genet feeds on small animals such
as birds and small rodents. Due to its great dexterity in catching
mice, it was often kept in houses, and we will see about
that in a second. Okay,
okay,
so let's take a look. So,
okay, okay, וחולדות סנאים מפני שעשויים לנקר את הבית, ve-khuldot sna'im mipnei
she-asuyim lenaker et ha-bayit, like I just said, because they clean out
the house. They eat up the rodents and the mice and they
keep the house clean, so those animals are permissible. Don't call those
a חיה דקה khaya daka or maybe they are a חיה דקה
khaya daka but we allow them. Okay,
מאי חולדות סנאים? mai khuldot sna'im? What are these weasels
of the, of the thorn bushes? אמר רב יהודה שרצא חרצא. amar
Rav Yehuda shartza khartza. So שרץ sheretz is like a, you know,
a
vermin, and
חרצא, khartza, so not exactly clear what this word חרצא khartza means.
But anyway, that's the name of it, שרצא חרצא. shartza khartza. Maybe
חרצא khartza is a type of a thorn bush or something. Okay,
ואיכא דאמרי, ve-ika d'amri, and some
say, חרזא, kharza, okay, it's called חרזא, kharza, or maybe שרצא חרזא.
shartza kharza. And what does it mean? דקטיני שקי, de-ktinei shakei, that
it's got small or short like legs, ורעי ביני ורדינא, ve-ra'ei beini
vardinei, and it grazes between thorn bushes.
Okay, ומאי שרצא? u-mai shartza? And now what's שרצא shartza if that's
what you call it, or actually תוספות Tosafot says שרצא shartza refers
to something that's not a שרצא חרצא, shartza khartza, a normal שרצא,
shartza, which is not allowed, דמטטי שקי, de-mtatei shakei, that its legs
are,
its legs or its thighs are like wide or very short, and
therefore it looks like it's slithering, which is more the שרצא. shartza.
This, the legs are more, you know, thin and not so short
and therefore it looks more like an animal and less slithering. Okay,
whatever, but that's what this is. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב עשינו
עצמנו בבבל כארץ ישראל לבהמה דקה. amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav asinu
atzmenu be-Vavel ke-Eretz Yisrael le-vehema daka. So now when we in בבל
Bavel we've treated ourselves like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael regarding small animals.
We extended the prohibition of grazing animals even to בבל. Bavel. Now
that's quite fascinating because even though, you know, so many Jews were
living in בבל, Bavel, the majority of the Jews in the גמרא's
Gemara period, but nevertheless,
it's not like it has the קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. It's not our homeland, maybe it's our adopted homeland, you know?
And so the concern for that,
for the landscape
and for the
general environment and the land in בבל Bavel to apply this גזירה
gezeira and to restrict people is pretty significant. Okay, now there's an
interesting question of what עשינו עצמנו asinu atzmenu means. Does it mean
that it was a new thing that we did? That's what it
sounds like. Or does it mean we realized that this was something
that always should have been from the time of the משנה? Mishna?
Here it sounds, you know, there's a similar discussion in גיטין Gittin
about a whole different issue where it might sound like it means
like we are claiming that even from the time of the משנה,
Mishna, בבל Bavel has the same status of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
It doesn't sound that way here. Okay, it sounds like this was
a new decision. אמר ליה רב אדא בר אהבה לרב הונא. amar
lei Rav Adda bar Ahava le-Rav Huna. So רב אדא בר אהבה
Rav Adda bar Ahava said to רב הונא, Rav Huna, דידך מאי?
didakh mai? So now if it applies in בבל, Bavel, so he
said to רב הונא, Rav Huna, what's your story? How is it
that you have small, how is it that you have sheep and
goat in your house? So אמר ליה, amar lei, דידן קא מנטרה
להו חובה. didan ka mantera lehu Khova. No, our small sheep and
our sheep and goat חובה, Khova, my wife, watches. אמר ליה, amar
lei, he said back to him, חובה תקברינהו לבנה. Khova tikberinhu le-vnah.
חובה Khova should bury her children, which is horrific to say such
a thing, a type of a curse. How dare you do that?
You know, and if that's what she's doing, she should bury her
children. Now תוספות Tosafot brings to soften it a little, which is
sort of saying like, "Does she want to bury her
children?" by she's spending all of her time watching the sheep and
the goat. Who's watching the kids?
So but he so that's a nice way to soften it, but
nevertheless, because he said those words, they had an impact. And then
the גמרא Gemara said כולה שני דרב אדא בר אהבה Kula shanei
deRav Adda bar Ahava as long as רב אדא בר אהבה Rav
Adda bar Ahava was alive after he had said those words, לא
איקיים זרע לרב הונא מחובה, Lo ikayam zara leRav Huna meChova, רב
הונא Rav Huna did not have a child that survived from חובה,
Chova, totally horrific story. Oh my God. And this is all a
new edict to apply this in בבל. Bavel. It's more it's less
about transgressing this edict and more about the power of the words
of רב הונא Rav Huna and being careful about our words.
Okay. איכא דאמרי Ika de'amrei some say אמר רב הונא אמר רב,
Amar Rav Huna amar Rav, so this was not a statement of
it wasn't אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav,
it was אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar Rav Huna amar Rav,
רב הונא Rav Huna who was just the one who was raising
the animals in the previous story, now he is saying it in
the name of רב. Rav. עשינו עצמין בבבל כארץ ישראל לבהמה דקה
Asinu atzmin beBavel keEretz Yisrael lebeheima daka מכי אתי רב לבבל. Mi-ki
ati Rav leBavel. Okay, we did it's not רב Rav is saying
it, but רב הונא Rav Huna is saying and some take out
the אמר רב. Amar Rav. He's not saying in the name of
רב Rav that when did this change? When רב Rav came to
בבל, Bavel, that's when we started to treat ourselves like ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and apply this גזירה gezeira in בבל Bavel as well.
Okay, now we're going to have an interesting story. רב
ושמואל ורב אסי, Rav veShmuel veRav Assi, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
and רב אסי Rav Assi איקלעו לבי שבוע הבן. Iklu lebei shevu'a
haben. They came to
a ברית. bris. ואיכא דאמרי Ve'ika de'amrei and some say לבי ישוע
הבן lebei Yeshu'a haben to a ישוע הבן Yeshu'a haben which רש''י
Rashi says is a פדיון הבן. pidyon haben.
תוספות Tosafos says that it's that ישוע הבן Yeshu'a haben is just
is a meal. If you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos, לבי
ישוע הבן, lebei Yeshu'a haben, he says פירוש קונטרס פדיון הבן וכן
הערוך Peirush kuntres pidyon haben vechen ha'aruch and he doesn't like that
explanation. So he says ורבינו תם פירוש שנולד שם בן ועל שם
שהולד נושע ונמלט מאמו veRabbeinu Tam peirush shenolad sham ben ve'al shem
shevlad nosha venimlat mi'imo that a child was born and because the
child was sort of saved or whatever taken from his mother כדכתיב
אם לזכר נחל לשון ישוע הבן. Kedichtiv im lezakhar nakhal lashon Yeshu'a
haben. והרגילו לעשות סעודה, Vehirgilu la'asot se'uda, they would do a סעודה
se'uda not just for a ברית מילה, bris mila, they would do
a סעודה se'uda because a child was born. So some actually want
to say that this is the source of the whole idea
of a שלום זכר shalom zachor to do a סעודה se'uda just
for the birth and not specifically for the ברית מילה. bris mila.
Okay, so they were going either to a ברית מילה bris mila
or פדיון הבן pidyon haben or שלום זכר. shalom zachor. רב לא
עייל קמיה דשמואל. Rav lo ayel kamei deShmuel. Now רב Rav had
made a decision that he was not going to enter in before
שמואל. Shmuel. Even though
שמואל Shmuel was more of a on a lower level than רב,
Rav, like a student, and רב Rav had higher status, nevertheless רב,
Rav, we're going to see in a minute why, רב Rav would
defer to שמואל Shmuel and he refused to enter before שמואל. Shmuel.
שמואל לא עייל קמיה דרב אסי. Shmuel lo ayel kamei deRav Assi.
Now שמואל Shmuel would refuse even to enter before רב אסי. Rav
Assi. רב אסי Rav Assi was a student of רב, Rav, but
the higher order, the hierarchy was רב רב אסי ושמואל. Rav, Rav
Assi, and Shmuel. So שמואל Shmuel wouldn't go before
רב אסי Rav Assi or רב. Rav. רב אסי לא עייל קמיה
דרב Rav Assi lo ayel kamei deRav and רב אסי Rav Assi
wouldn't go before רב. Rav. So who's going to go first? Nobody
can go first. It's like the fox and the farmer and you
have to cross the river. Anyway, so what are you going to
do? אמרי מאן ניטרח, Amrei man nitrach, who is going to be
the one that's going to hold back? One of if all of
them come to the door first, then everybody's going to say after
you. So let's make it that one person stays back and the
rest of us go to the door so we don't have to
choose when we get to the front door. ניטרח שמואל, Nitrach Shmuel,
let שמואל Shmuel stay back, וניזיל רב ורב אסי Veneizil Rav veRav
Assi and רב Rav and רב אסי Rav Assi will go. רב
Rav will go first because he is at the top of and
then רב אסי Rav Assi will follow him and then שמואל Shmuel
will come, which is anyway the right order as we're going to
see because שמואל Shmuel is considered to be at the bottom of
all this hierarchy. So the גמרא Gemara says וניטרח רב או רב
אסי, Venitrach Rav o Rav Assi, so why not let רב Rav
or רב אסי Rav Assi hang back? It should be רב ורב
אסי Rav and Rav Assi and let שמואל Shmuel go first. Okay,
or no, I guess if one of them is hanging back. Anyway,
no, it had to be רב ורב אסי. Rav and Rav Assi.
Anyway, רב מילתא בעלמא הוא
דעבד ליה לשמואל Rav milta be'alma hu de'avid lei leShmuel because רב
Rav was just it wasn't that שמואל'ס Shmuel's at a higher level,
he was just doing him a courtesy. There's no question that רב
Rav should have been the one to go first, but רב Rav
was doing a courtesy to שמואל. Shmuel. Why? משום ההוא מעשה דלטייה.
Mishum hahu ma'ase dilaitya. Okay, there was a story that he accidentally
cursed him. I mean we just got through a story of accidentally
being cursed, this רב חובה Rav Chova of חובה, Chova, the wife
of רב הונא. Rav Huna. So here רב Rav in another story
accidentally had cursed שמואל, Shmuel, עד דבעי רחמי עליה. ad barei Rav
lei. So רב Rav actually showed this type of deference to שמואל.
Shmuel. But really רב Rav was at the top of the hierarchy,
so it made sense for שמואל Shmuel to hang back and we
would go in the right order רב ורב אסי ושמואל. Rav and
then Rav Assi and then Shmuel. Okay, now why are we talking
about this? Because אדהכי והכי Adahachi vehachi while they were sort of
debating how we're going to do this, who's going to hang back
and who's going to go first, אתא שונרא Ata shunra came a
cat, פסקה ליד דינוקא Paskeih leyad de'inoka and chopped and bit off
the hand of the child. the hand of this baby that they
were going for the ברית bris or the פדיון הבן. pidyon haben.
Horrific story. I mean obviously this does not mean like a nice
tame cat, could be like a cougar or something like that. נפק
רב ודרש Nafak Rav v'darash so רב Rav went out and he
taught the following הלכה. halacha. חתול
מותר להרגו Chatul muttar le'hargo a cat you're allowed a cat is
dangerous and therefore you're allowed to go ahead anybody is allowed to
go kill it to get rid of this dangerous animal from among
us.
ואסור לקיימו v'assur l'kaymo and it's forbidden for anybody to keep a
cat again maybe he means more like a large cat or something
or a dangerous cat I assume we'll see in a minute. ואין
בו משום גזל v'ein bo mishum gezel and if somebody were to
steal it it wouldn't be גזל gezel ואין בו משום השבת אבידה
v'ein bo mishum hashavas aveida and if you found it you have
no obligation to return it לבעלים. le'ba'alim.
So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute וכיון דאמרת מותר להרגו
v'keivan demart muttar le'hargo once you say you're allowed to kill it
מאי ניהו תו אסור לקיימו mai neihu tu assur le'kaymo so what
why do you have to tell me that it's forbidden to hold
it to own it isn't that obvious? No מה דתימא ma'd'teima אם
דאית מותר להרגו im d'it muttar le'hargo איסורא ליכא issura leika it's
permitted for somebody to kill it but there's no prohibition if I
want to keep on owning
it people have permission to kill it but nobody's stop telling me
not to own it קמשמע לן Kamashmalan that no everybody is forbidden
to own it.
Okay אמרי Amri וכיון דאמרת אין בו משום גזל v'keivan d'amarta ein
bo mishum gezel one minute but if you're saying that there's no
problem of stealing it מאי ניהו תו אין בו משום השבת אבידה
mai neihu tu ein bo mishum hashavas aveida obviously there's no problem
of obligation to return it לבעלים le'ba'alim so אמר רבינא Amar Ravina
לעורו. l'oro. No it means let's say there's a dead cat and
you don't even have to and now you can use the or
lion or cougar whatever the skin now that's something that can be
used but since the owner wasn't supposed to own it you don't
even have to return that to the owner and you can keep
that for yourself. Okay so we really wanted to make sure that
these were gotten rid of. Now מיתיבי meisivei רבן שמעון בן אלעזר
אומר Rabban Shimon ben Elazar omer one minute I'll challenge you on
this. We taught a ברייתא baraita רבן שמעון בן אלעזר אומר Rabban
Shimon ben Elazar omer מגדלים כלבים כופרין וחתולין וקופין וחולדות סנאיים מפני
שעשויים לנקר את הבית m'gadlim klavim kofirin v'chatulin v'kofin v'chuldo snayim mipnei
she'assu l'nakos et habayis what we just taught is you're allowed to
have these types of small animals because they keep the house clean
from vermin and rodents and so on so how could רב Rav
go ahead and rule against this? It seems like it was ruled
that it was permissible.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult
הא באוכמא הא בחיורא ha b'uchma ha b'chivra difference is between black
and white. Okay so white are the dangerous
ones excuse me yes white are the dangerous ones and black are
the safe ones so the black ones are okay what רב Rav
was saying was that the white ones were no good. So the
גמרא Gemara says והא מעשה דרב אוכמא הוה v'ha maiseh d'Rav uchma
hava and I don't know how the גמרא Gemara knows it but
the גמרא Gemara says the story of רב Rav was a black
one so I thought if you're saying the black are tame it
seems like רב Rav is making a גזירה gezeira even about the
black ones. So no התם אוכמא בר חיורא הוה. hasam uchma bar
chivra hava. No no no that was a black one that was
born from a white one so therefore it was still of a
dangerous type הוה hava והמיבעיא בעי ליה רבינא v'ha mibaya baya lei
Ravina but one minute didn't רבינא Ravina ask this question דבעי רבינא
אוכמא בר חיורא מהו d'baya Ravina uchma bar chivra mahu we know
that white is no good and black is okay what about a
black one that's an offspring of a white? כי קמיבעיא Ki ka
mibaya so and רבינא Ravina didn't have an answer so why is
it what it's like obvious to רב Rav that it's a problem?
So you could say yes but okay no כי קמיבעיא ליה לרבינא
באוכמא בר חיורא בר אוכמא ki ka mibaya lei lei Ravina b'uchma
bar chivra bar uchma רבינא Ravina's question was black the son of
a white the son of a black. The grandfather was black so
it's coming from it originates from a family that's black so therefore
it's probably tamer does the fact that its parent was white make
it a problem? מעשה דרב באוכמא בר חיורא בר חיורא הוה Maiseh
d'Rav b'uchma bar chivra bar chivra hava but רב Rav's story was
a case of a black that was born from a white from
a line of white cats and
therefore it was a much more dangerous one. How you're supposed to
know is not at all clear but anyway bottom line is the
גמרא Gemara is saying that some of these cats were dangerous and
forbidden and others were seen as legitimate to own in order to
keep your house clean from mice and rats and vermin.
Okay here we go. אמר רבי אחא בר פפא משום רבי אבא
בר פפא Amar Rabi Acha bar Papa mishum Rabi Abba bar Papa
this now is going to sound like when you make a סיום
siyum we're going to have a lot of בר פפא'ס. Bar Pappas.
Okay said רבי אחא בר פפא Rabi Acha bar Papa in the
name of רבי אבא בר פפא Rabi Abba bar Papa משום רבי
אדא בר פפא mishum Rabi Adda bar Papa in the name of
רבי אדא בר פפא. Rabi Adda bar Papa. ואמרי לה אמר רבי
אבא בר פפא משום רבי חייא בר פפא משום רבי אחא בר
פפא V'amrei la Amar Rabi Abba bar Papa mishum Rabi Chiya bar
Papa mishum Rabi Acha bar Papa that's another version of the tradition.
ואמרי לה אמר רבי אבא בר פפא משום רבי אחא בר פפא
משום רבי חנינא בר פפא. V'amrei la Amar Rabi Abba bar Papa
mishum Rabi Acha bar Papa mishum Rabi Chanina bar Papa. Okay anyway
one of these brothers were saying it in the name of one
and saying it in the name of the other. מתריעין על החיכוך
בשבת Matri'in al hachichuch b'shabbos you can make blasts over חיכוך hachichuch
which is a type of a like a type of a blister
and boils on שבת Shabbos because you're afraid that this is going
to be like contagious and it's going to spread and you'd have
to do a תענית ta'anis and so on. Now רש"י Rashi says
the blast means with like a שופר shofar תוספות Tosafos says no
obviously we're not talking about that but we are talking about that
you can like have עננו aneinu and a תענית ta'anis and cry
out okay for that on שבת Shabbos now that's not relevant to
us that's more relevant for מסכת תענית masechet ta'anis ודלת הננעלת לא
במהרה תפתח v'deles hane'elet lo b'meheira tipatach and a door that is
closed will not quickly open you know you have to stay seize
opportunity and if you miss when you have that little opening of
opportunity it's going to be really hard to find it again. So
you know there's a door of opportunity that's closing and you have
to don't think you know you have to grab opportunity when it
presents itself. Okay? So the door that closes will not quickly open
again והלוקח בית בארץ ישראל כותבין עליו אונו אפילו בשבת. V'halokeach bayis
b'Eretz Yisrael kosvin alav ono afilu b'Shabbos. And a person who purchases
a house in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you can because and this
seems to be why we're bringing it here because of our concern
about יישוב ארץ ישראל yishuv Eretz Yisrael and the Jewish settlement in
Israel and keeping the land good and keeping Jews present which is
you know and owning homes and owning places in Israel which is
a very big concern in מסכת עבודה זרה. Maseches Avoda Zara. So
this that's why it's presumably we're quoting this here. And therefore you're
allowed to write the deed even on שבת. Shabbos. So that seems
a little wild so we'll get back to that in a second.
מיתיבי על כלחנית Meisvei al kalchanis ושאר פורעניות המתרגשות ובאות על ציבור
v'shear puraniyos hamisragshos uva'os al tzibur we teach in תענית Taanis that
when there's other bad things that are happening to the community כגון
חיכוך kigon chichuch like this case of this חיכוך chichuch which we
mentioned before this type of blister or
boil חגב chagav זבוב zvuv צירעה ויתוש tzira v'yitush ושילוח נחשים v'shiluach
nechashim ועקרבים v'akrabim לא היו מתריעין אלא צועקין. lo hayu matri'in ela
tzo'akin. You wouldn't do מתריעין matri'in you would do צועקין. tzo'akin.
Now for רש"י Rashi the difference is between like you wouldn't do
a שופר shofar you would actually just call out in
תפילה. tfila. For תוספות Tosfos it seems the difference might be between
whether you'd do it on שבת Shabbos or do it on the
weekday but whatever מתריעין matri'in means you said we would be מתריעין
matri'in and this says that we're not מתריעין. matri'in. לא קשיא Lo
kashya כאן בלח כאן ביבש kan b'lach kan b'yavesh
the difference is whether it's moist or dry. Okay if it is
moist it is considered to be you know more dangerous. So let's
take a look. דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי D'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi שחין שהביא הקדוש ברוך הוא על המצרים shchin sheheivi Hakadosh Baruch
Hu al Hamitzrim the boils that God brought to the Egyptians לח
מבחוץ ויבש מבפנים lach mibachutz v'yavesh mibifnim was moist on the outside
and dry on the inside so that's like the worst that's the
most dangerous and therefore that would be the one that you would
be מתריעין matri'in even on מתריעין matri'in even on שבת. Shabbos. שנאמר
והיה שחין אבעבועות פורח באדם ובבהמה. Shene'emar v'hi shchin ava'bu'os poreach ba'adam
uvab'heima.
The שחין shchin would be boiling and sprouting forth so meaning it'd
be moist on the outside but שחין shchin is understood to be
dry on the inside so that would be the worst and that
you could call out or blow שופר shofar even on שבת. Shabbos.
That was the first דרשה. d'rasha. ודלת הנעולה לא במהרה תפתח V'deles
hane'ulah lo bimeheira tipasach and a door that's closing
will
not open again quickly so seize the opportunity when it presents itself.
מאי היא Mai hi? מר זוטרא אמר סמיכה. Mar Zutra amar smicha.
If you have you know this was the סמיכה smicha going all
the way back to משה רבנו Moshe Rabbeinu and it was at
a certain time it was actually very precarious whether it was going
to be able to continue. So if you're in a position and
you're being offered סמיכה smicha then you know seize the opportunity when
it presents itself. סמיכה smicha רב אשי אמר כל המריעין לו לא
במהרה מטיבין לו. Rav Ashi amar kol hamarei'in lo lo bimeheira meitivin
lo. רב אשי Rav Ashi said
anybody who does it's bad is done to him will
not quickly be done good to him. So it sounds like something
actively bad but it also can mean that again that it was
bad because you lost the opportunity it's not going to quickly get
that opportunity again could be understood to be similar to the earlier
point. רב אחא מדפתי אמר לעולם אין מטיבין לו Rav Acha miDifti
amar l'olam ein meitivin lo you'll that you'll never be good again.
ולאו היא V'lav hi רב אחא מדפתי מילתא דנפשיה הוא דקא אמר.
Rav Acha miDifti milsa d'nafshai hu d'ka amar. רב אחא מדפתי Rav
Acha miDifti that was what happened in his particular case. In his
particular case he had an opportunity to get a position of authority
and he let it pass by and he was never able to
get it again so that made him be more pessimistic and say
you'll never get it again rather than it'll be hard to get
it again. תוספות Tosfos actually points out that in a different גמרא
Gemara about in that story itself where that opportunity passed him up
he said he said it won't quickly present itself again. תוספות Tosfos
says well initially he said it won't quickly happen again and then
after he didn't get it and he never got it again he
switched his tune and he said if you lost an opportunity you'll
never get it again. It's a little sad commentary.
Okay now we get to the one that seems to be most
relevant for us and also you know a very shocking הלכה halachicly
so let's take a look.
והלוקח בית בארץ ישראל כותבין עליו אונו אפילו בשבת V'halokeach bayis b'Eretz
Yisrael kosvin alav ono afilu b'Shabbos and someone who buys a house
in Israel you can write the deed even on
שבת. Shabbos. גמרא Gemara בשבת סלקא דעתך b'Shabbos salka da'atach? Do you
really think you could do it on שבת? Shabbos? How could you
do it on
שבת? Shabbos? That's a מלאכה דאורייתא. melacha d'Oraisa. אלא כדאמר רבא התם
אומרו לנוכרי ועושה Ela k'd'amar Rava hasam omru l'nochri v'oseh like רבא
Rava said in a different case no no no not you write
it you get it written you tell a non-Jew to write the
deed. Okay and that way you make it and that's maybe also
similar to the previous point an opportunity presents itself you gotta seize
it. So it's an opportunity
to buy property in Israel, we want Jews to own property, you
seize it. And you get the non-Jew to do it even though
obviously normally you could not tell a non-Jew to do מלאכה, melacha,
here we allow it. הכא נמי, hacha nami, so the same way
רבא Rava said that case about a different case about telling a
non-Jew here too, אומר לנכרי ועושה, omer le-nochri ve-oseh, you tell a
non-Jew. ואף על גב דאמירה לנכרי שבות, ve-af al gav de-amira le-nochri
shvut, even though obviously telling a non-Jew to do מלאכה melacha on
שבת shabbos is a rabbinic violation, משום ישוב ארץ ישראל mishum yishuv
eretz yisrael לא גזרו בה רבנן, lo gazru bah rabanan, in order
to settle ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael the rabbis did you know did
not make a גזירה gezeira and permitted it. This leads to a
big question about when is אמירה לנכרי amira le-nochri permissible. Is אמירה
לנכרי amira le-nochri permissible only for you know to do a you
know for a מצוה mitzvah like ארץ ישראל? eretz yisrael? So can
is it אמירה לנכרי amira le-nochri permissible for any מצוה? mitzvah? So
there's a radical position you know that תוספות tosfos quotes of the
of the
הלכות
גדולות halachos gedolos that said that you're allowed to do אמירה לנכרי
amira le-nochri for a דאורייתא de-oraisa not only for you know for
ישוב ארץ ישראל yishuv eretz yisrael like this case but even for
ברית מילה. bris milah. Now maybe that's only ברית מילה bris milah
because ברית מילה bris milah itself is דוחה שבת doche shabbos so
the case there was like מכשירי ברית מילה, machshirei bris milah, the
act of ברית מילה bris milah is דוחה שבת doche shabbos but
not let's say if you have to you know bring the knife
or sharpen the knife or you know bring the baby or some
type of a thing like that and the בה"ג bahag allows אמירה
לנכרי amira le-nochri for things relating to the ברית מילה. bris milah.
And there were some opinion that even allow אמירה לנכרי amira le-nochri
for a דאורייתא de-oraisa for you know for other צרכי מצוה tzorchei
mitzvah especially things that are let's say צרכי רבים. tzorchei rabim. So
that's part of a discussion in הלכה. halacha. There's the opposite extreme
doesn't allow אמירה לנכרי amira le-nochri even for under for a דרבנן
de-rabanan what's called a שבות דשבות במקום מצוה shvut de-shvut bemakom mitzvah
doesn't allow even an אמירה amira for דרבנן de-rabanan for sake of
a מצוה. mitzvah. The general consensus is that אמירה לנכרי amira le-nochri
is permitted for a דרבנן de-rabanan for the sake of a מצוה
mitzvah but not for a דאורייתא de-oraisa for the sake of a
מצוה mitzvah and the case here of ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael is
an exception. Okay, just to end this, אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני
אמר רבי יונתן, amar rabbi shmuel bar nachmani amar rabbi yonatan, הלוקח
עיר בארץ ישראל כופין אותו ליקח לו דרך מארבע רוחותיה. halokeach ir
be-eretz yisrael kofin oso likach lo derech me-arba ruchoseha.
Somebody purchases a town in ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael in the land
of Israel, right? I mean you know it's like beyond my understanding
what it means to own a whole town but anyway you force
the person to also purchase pathways in all four
directions משום ישוב ארץ ישראל mishum yishuv eretz yisrael which I don't
exactly understand. I guess it means that if somebody else owns the
paths they can close off access so you have to purchase the
paths to ensure that the access from other places to there and
there to other places is always open. Okay, we will stop here
for now.